This is my kitchen table and also my
filing system.
Over much of the past three decades,
I've been an investor the highest
calling of mankind.
I've often thought was private equity.
And then I started interviewing.
I watch your interview.
Those I know how to do something.
I've learned in doing my interviews, how
leaders make it to the top.
I asked him how much you want to listen
to.
50.
I said, Fine.
I didn't negotiate with him.
I didn't know due diligence to have
something I'd like to sell and how they
stay there.
You don't feel inadequate now because
being only the second wealthiest man in
the world.
Is that right?
One of the most celebrated artists in
the world today is Jeff Koons.
He's known for his paintings, but also
particularly well known for his
sculptures.
Had a chance recently to sit down with
Jeff Koons to talk about how he went
from being a commodities broker on Wall
Street to one of the most celebrated
artists in the world.
So you were one of the most famous
artists in the world today.
Did you ever think when you were selling
bonds for or commodities for Smith
Barney that you would be one of the
world's most famous artists?
I wanted to participate, so I can't say
that I thought, you know, that I would
reach
as much of a level.
I'm very grateful for that.
I wanted to be a part of a group of
artists, the dialogue of art, how it can
affect our lives.
Most artists are probably specialists in
paintings or maybe ceramics or maybe in
sculptures.
But you do all of that, and your your
works are going for very high prices in
all of these areas.
So what is it that has enabled you to be
a painter that's able to sell works for
very high prices?
And a sculptor and a ceramicist as well?
I think it's about focusing on what's
really kind of relevant to you, to
remove fear,
to be able to be engaged with the world,
to open yourself up, to experience.
So I think somewhere along the way,
David, I was very fortunate and to enjoy
the feelings and the sensations that the
body and the mind create when you have
experience.
How is the art world changed since you
entered it a few decades ago as a young
artist?
Today, I think artists are more
isolated.
When I came into the New York art world
in the mid-seventies, you know, we
really it was smaller and we had people
like Lichtenstein and, you know, Warhol,
Johns, Rauschenberg, all of these people
that we really looked up to because, you
know, these were real artists.
They just wanted to participate, make
art.
But at the same time, they were being
able to succeed in representing that
fine art.
Artists were participating in culture.
I think before this generation, people
in America would think of culture being
music entertainment, but they didn't
really think of the fine art artists as
really being relevant to culture.
I think they changed that.
Leo Castelli took Johns and Rauschenberg
to meet President Kennedy.
Artists were, you know, being invited to
the White House.
They were being looked at as
participants in culture.
So is there any one artist that you
would say inspired you to become an
artist or who you most admire now?
You know, I love all art.
So many artists I enjoy all through
history from this moment, you know, all
the way back to, you know, choosing like
a pale, mythic object.
But when I was younger, Dali was very
important.
My parents bought me a coffee table book
of Dali's work.
It was beautiful with persistent memory
on the cover.
And eventually, when I am a teenager,
when I was 19, I met Dali and I called
him up.
My mother told me she read that he was
staying at the St Regis Hotel half the
year, and he picked up the phone and he
invited me to come to New York that
weekend.
And if I would meet him in the lobby at
12:00, you know, right at noon, he would
meet with me.
Now, I Salvador Dali was famous for
different kinds of art, very unusual in
many ways.
But he also had a very unusual mustache,
very thin.
And as a young man, did you not have a
similar mustache kind of to copy him?
Well, no, I liked his mustache and I
loved to reference it in different
artworks.
Now, when you started working in art
world, you were more of a painter than a
sculptor.
Was that fair to say?
I always was a painter.
Always a painter in college.
You know, I'm making paintings, but my
paintings start to become so physical.
I start adding little porcelain figures
like these figures around us.
Small models, though.
In porcelain to my paintings, they
become so big and heavy I have to take
my paintings off the wall.
I set them this one painting on a table
and I put two inflatables beside it.
One was an inflatable elephant.
Inflatable panda.
They were the first inflatables I worked
with.
But that's when I started to go into
sculpture.
Okay, so you're a painter initially, and
you're still a painter.
But many people, if I mention the name
Jeff Koons, they will say he did the dog
or the bunny or other animals or other
well-known objects.
And so when did you come up with the
idea of doing these animals and in
stainless steel with these very vivid
colors?
I always enjoyed Robert Smithson's work,
minimalist work.
Judd And but I remember seeing
Smithson's mirror pieces and I enjoyed
them, and so I decided to buy some.
You know, hardware store prefab cut mere
12 by 12 inch mirrors.
And I put to it on the wall like a 45
degree angle off the wall, two on the
floor.
And I sat in two inflatable flowers, one
kind of a little masculine standing
upright and one that was round.
And then I did one with a rabbit, an
inflatable rabbit.
And so these pieces, that's when I
started to really feel like I was
starting to contribute something to the
dial, taking an inflatable rabbit, and
then do you kind of wrap it in steel as
well?
These were readymades.
These were just inflatables, but I would
just set them and let them display
themselves.
And eventually I'd go on and I'm making
vacuum cleaners where I'm letting vacuum
cleaners just display their newness
inside these vitrines.
I'm always working with readymade
objects.
And even today, the works that we see
even around me are based in readymade
objects.
And the reason I do that, David, is to
try to communicate to people that
everything is accessible.
There should be no judgment, just be
open to every well, let's take the dogs,
for example.
Very famous dogs.
You have the they look like balloon kind
of figures to some extent.
How do you make those?
In the case of the balloon dog, I blew
up a balloon dog.
So I had this balloon, which is kind of
like a latex type of a piece, molded it,
cast it, and then blew that up in scale
and put it into a clay and eventually
had that transformed into stainless
steel and then put trance mirrored the
stainless steel.
If you look at the works around me,
these are both sculptures and paintings.
This piece of Diana, there were 6000 3D
masks that were used to be able to paint
this piece.
So when you bring both the 3D and the 2D
together, I believe that's art.
But suppose you're a painter as you are
and you paint it, you have a canvas in
your painting and then you're done.
When you're finished with this kind of,
let's say, the dog, you've got to get
the you're going to blow up the balloon,
then you got to put some material around
it, then you got to do it in stainless
steel and then you got to put a color
around it.
That's a lot of work.
Did you ever say it's too much work for
one piece of art?
Well, it's it is a lot of work and a lot
of time goes by.
And I also had to develop a studio of
people to work with me to be able to
make works like that, to make something
like a large balloon dog on your own.
It would be very, very difficult.
Now, one of the pieces that I always
like that you've done is the Play-Doh.
How many of those did you make?
Five.
Now, where did you get the idea for
Play-Doh?
My one son was playing with a mound of
Play-Doh.
I was playing with them, but I was doing
something else.
And he said, Dad.
And I looked, and he went in front of
his mound of Play-Doh.
He went, Wallah.
And I thought I looked at the mound and
his gesture and I thought, this is what
I'm trying to do every day to make
something that you really can't make a
judgment about.
I mean, it's just perfect in its being.
It's it's fantastic.
You have lots of different types of
works of art.
Let me mention another type shrubbery,
art, where you make a big sculpture, but
it's got like shrubbery around it.
I've seen some of them topiary.
Yes, I made two ones called Puppy and I
made that in 1992.
And then in 2000 I made one called Split
Rocker.
Puppy is now where one is in front of
the Bilbao Museum in Spain in
Guggenheim.
And there's another version of that that
hasn't been installed yet that I believe
will be in the United States.
Now at Gladstone, which is a private
museum in Potomac, Maryland, created by
Mitch Rales.
I think you have something there that's
like one of those works of art.
Is that right?
Yes.
That's called Split Rocker.
Okay.
It's larger than Puppy.
Puppy takes about anywhere from 45 to
60000 plants.
And actually, the split rocker goes from
about 60 to 90, depending on your
planning.
You have designed a train, which I
thought was once going to be put over
the High Line in New York.
But now it didn't get there.
Where is the train of you designed it
and it's gigantic, isn't it?
And where will it ultimately go?
Still just a model.
It's 166 feet tall and this train that
hangs performs.
So it's an old Baldwin train.
It's new, but it's a 2900 series engine
that we've rebuilt with different
steam generators and different ways of
creating all the optics of the wheels
turning and everything.
And what takes place at least one time
of day, the train would start up and
everything that a real train would do,
leaving the station, this train hanging
from the crane will do so very slowly.
You know, It's like, ding, ding, ding,
ding.
And then true.
True.
And, you know, the train's a breathing
machine just like we are.
So people can relate to that.
So you're going to build it.
I hope it gets built.
And I've been in dialogue with Qatar.
They've shown interest.
So I hope that it gets built.
And that's something that for my own
legacy, I hope that within my interest
in public sculpture gets me.
Let's talk about your beginning and how
you became an artist.
So many artists are born in famous
cities known for art.
Paris, Rome, London, New York.
Were you born in any of those famous
cities known for creating great artists?
No.
I was born in York, Pennsylvania.
But Pennsylvania is known for some great
artists.
You know, Warhol has come from
Pittsburgh, Keith Haring, Kutztown,
Andrew Wyeth.
Many artists have come from Pittsburgh,
the Calder family.
Where did you get the inspiration to be
an artist from?
I learned aesthetics through my dad.
When he was younger, he worked in a
furniture store and he went off to World
War Two.
And when he came back, he went back to
this interior decorating store where he
worked as a child and he became an
interior decorator.
And my dad was great.
I mean, he really developed he had a
very aesthetic way of looking at things.
And your mother, was she interested in
the art world?
My mother went to college.
So I think a desire for developing my
intellect,
I think I could attribute to my mother.
How did you do in high school?
Were you an artist in high school?
I was always in the art class.
You go to Baltimore for the Maryland
Institute of Arts and you later transfer
to the Art Institute School in Chicago.
Why did you move from Baltimore to
Chicago?
I was a very ambitious artist in school,
and my artworks were being shown in the
president's office at Maryland Institute
College of Art.
But I came to New York and I sold the
gym, not show at the Whitney.
And this was in 1974.
And I decided that this was a type of
art work that I could relate to.
And Jim Nutz work was about personal
iconography, but it was still very tied
to pop art and to art history.
And I was attracted to that because I
love Dada and Surrealism, and Chicago
was really the hub for this type work.
They were called the Chicago Images.
So you graduate, you have a diploma.
Where do you go next?
I applied to graduate school, but I was
not accepted and I decided just to stay
in Chicago.
And I was working at like Carson Perry,
Scott, one of the department stores,
doing display work.
And I heard Patti Smith's album Horses.
And when I heard that album and the
deejay on the radio in Chicago was
talking about a scene in New York of
young artists and poets and everybody
hanging out in this scene.
I got up and I hitchhiked to New York
the next day, and I've been here really
ever since then.
So you moved to New York, and then when
you're in New York, are you doing art
work or are you getting other things
done to pay the rent?
Well, I'm trying to make artwork, but I
also have to support myself.
I went to Museum of Modern Art and I
applied for this type of job to move
artworks.
They said, Look, Jeff, you're calling
every day.
We don't have a preparatory job, but if
your work in the membership Development
Department, there's an opening is in the
ticket booth selling tickets and you
just.
Would you work in the ticket booth?
I said, Absolutely.
And that's how I started at MoMA.
And then during breaks, I would start to
promote their membership.
But how did you wind up selling
commodities at Smith Barney?
Because you did that for a while, too,
right?
People would come up to me and they
would, you know, take out a membership
and they'd say, Jeff, you know, why
don't you come and work for me?
So I ended up thinking that for the type
of works that I wanted to make, I really
had to raise my income.
So I left the museum and I went into
becoming registered.
I started off selling mutual funds.
I would go door to door, you know,
basically.
I mean, I would call and make
appointments.
Then eventually I became registered for
commodities.
And, you know, being a broker, it's a
it's a salesperson.
I mean, I was trying to bring in people.
I wasn't an analyst, but I was a
registered broker.
So when you're doing this, you're
selling commodities and, you know,
you're trying to convince people to buy
open accounts and so forth.
Did you ever think I'm really going to
be a famous artist someday?
I can't say I was thinking about being
famous.
I wanted to participate.
You know, I wanted to give it everything
I had.
I always think about leading to the best
of my ability.
And I would say yes to everything.
If somebody had asked me to be in an
exhibition, I would tell them yes.
And I would try to participate, make the
best work that I could.
I was ambitious.
I had tremendous respect for artists
like Warhol and Lichtenstein, but my
ambition wasn't the fame.
It was to be part of a group
the power, the power of art, the
transcending power of becoming a person.
I want to become the person I could
become.
When did you say, okay, I'm good enough
as an artist to sell some art and I
don't need to sell commodities anymore?
I reached a point where I couldn't think
about anything other than my work, so I,
you know, should be trying to, you know,
open some more accounts, be able to give
more service to people.
But instead, I'd be on the phone talking
to Dr.
Richard Feynman and talking about
equilibrium and how can I get permanent
equilibrium?
Can I do it really within the confines
of an aquarium?
And I couldn't think about anything
else.
And so I was accepting, you know, all
the ramifications that if I made a show
and it wasn't successful, that, you
know, maybe I have to go pump gas, I
have to start all over.
But I didn't have any options.
Richard Feynman, for those who don't
know, is one of the most famous
physicists of the 20th century Nobel
Prize winner, among other things.
How did you get him on the phone?
I called him, and so I was in an
airplane flying back, I think, from Los
Angeles.
And I saw that he had just released the
book.
Surely you're joking, Dr.
Feynman.
And I thought, oh, my gosh, this I was
reading that he loves to play bongos and
he likes art.
He paints.
So after, you know, a day when I landed,
I called up Feynman and I told him the
work that I wanted to create.
I want to create these equilibrium
tanks.
But I was worried that I didn't know how
to create permanent equilibrium in such
a confined space.
And he told me I could do it.
So were you looking for new things that
you haven't conquered yet?
I've always loved philosophy, and I
think one of the reasons I work with a
reflective surface is because in
philosophy, the word you notice the most
is to reflect and reflection.
I want to continue to reflect.
I want to continue to be calm.
You know, the art happens inside us.
These objects aren't art.
They're just paintings.
They're just forms.
But art is really the essence that we
can feel as people of our own potential.
So if somebody is watching and says, I
want to be the next Jeff Koons, what
advice would you give to that person?
I would tell them to trust in
themselves.
After you trust in yourself, you want to
go outside yourself.
And if you really focus on your
interests, it connects you to a
universal vocabulary.
You.
So what is it that you think makes an
artist who goes from being a not well
known, maybe struggling artist to being
a famous artist?
I think my family gave me a lot of
support, emotional support when I was
younger.
I can't say that I was a loner growing
up, but, you know, I was thinking
philosophically and my mind was
wondering about what the possibilities I
could find in life.
But to be able to be part of a group was
really meaningful to me, and the art
world represented that.
So if somebody is watching and says, I
want to be the next Jeff Koons, I want
to be a famous artist.
What advice would you give to that
person?
I would tell them to trust in themselves
and to focus on your interests.
And what I found in my own life that
when I really focus on my interests and
there was a certain point where I
learned how to trust in myself, when
after you trust in yourself, you want to
go outside yourself.
And if you really focus on your
interests, it connects you to a
universal vocabulary.
Now, did your parents live to see your
success as a famous artist?
They did.
And, you know, I'm very grateful that
they were able to see that the type of
support that they gave to me to be able
to believe in myself.
They brought me up also to be
self-reliant, that I was able to at
least accomplish part of my dreams that
they saw.
So a new world you want to conquer are
just continuing to find new ways to
express yourself in art.
And you're sounds like you're a very
happy person.
I want to be, you know, a greater
person.
I won't be the best person I can be.
I want to be the best artist I can be.
The role models for me.
Artists like Titian and Picasso,
Matisse.
These artists got better and better the
older they got.
I mean, late Titian,
you know, it's.
It's incredible.
Not that you're going anywhere anytime
soon, but what would you like your
legacy to be?
David I would hope that I could be
somewhat of a role model that if I've
been able to accomplish what I have been
able to, that anybody feels like they
can do it too.
That if they have the interests that
they would really like to participate,
be involved in the dialog of art.
You know, art's so amazing.
I mean, I was this kid from Pennsylvania
who went to art school.
But art connects you to all the human
disciplines.
Art is not this hierarchy.
The whole idea of a hierarchy that you
need to be informed about something, it
doesn't exist.
People do that for their own kind of
empowerment to disempower you, the
viewer.
You don't need anything in art other
than your own past experience to that
moment.
And I hope that I'm a symbol of that.
Who?